HDFC Ergo Optima Secure 50 ICICI LBRD
Elevate 45 Care Supreme 45 Care Health
Insurance Ultimate Care Plan 122
Aditya Birla Active One 56 Pages This
is not a metric or ratio.  This is the
number of pages in the policy wording documents of your health insurance plan.  And
that's why we never read these policy wording
documents.
The language is difficult and the truth is
that health insurance companies also
know this.  That is why
they adopt such a casual approach at the time of claim
because they know that the policy holder has
never read the policy contract.
But if I tell you that policy
wording is not a randomly written document where
anything is written somewhere
which is very difficult to find.  It has a
proper sequence and structure which has been
defined by IRDA.  It is just like
inside a book you
get chapters, table of contents
which makes it easy for you to find any information.
Similarly,
in health insurance policy wordings,
if you know two things:
how many sections are there in this policy wording, that is,
how many chapters are there and
what information is written in which section, then you
can directly jump to the page which
information you need.  Hello friends,
my name is Ravindra Singh and in the next few
minutes, you and I are going to decode the
structure and sequence of health insurance policy warnings
which will
work exactly like a GPS.   That
means you have any question in your mind
while purchasing a health insurance policy or the company
rejects your claim.   I do
n't understand the exclusions.  There
is some term or clause of the health insurance company
which you are not able to understand.
What is the list of non-medical items
?  How many types of Anne are there?
Where is all this written in your health insurance policy wordings?  You will
understand exactly in today's video.  Just
think
how many thousand rupees you have paid to your health insurance company as annual premium.
But this video which will
teach you how to read policy wordings is
absolutely free.  But you will
definitely have to invest some of your time in this video.
So let's start the video and
decode the health insurance policy
wordings structure.
Friends in this video I am using
HDFC Ergo Optima Secure Policy
Wordings document so that we can
understand all the sections and the entire structure.
Any policy wording document may have
six to eight sections,
beginning with a preamble.
It is mentioned in the preamble whether this is a
policy contract or not?
Why are the terms and conditions
written in it?  Basically it is told
who has issued this policy contract?  So
here is the name of the company which will later be
referred to as the company again and again in this policy warning document.  Apart from this, the person who will be
covered under this policy will be
called the policy holder and the rest of the people will
also be called insured persons under this policy.
And this health
insurance policy that the company is issuing for you is being
issued on the basis of the information you have given in the proposal form.
These things are mentioned in this preamble.   The
first preamble section is legally very
important for the company to define, but as a
policy holder it is not very important for us.
After the preamble, the second part comes which is the
operating clause.  It has been defined in this
that under what circumstances a
claim can be made from this policy.  For example,
if any insured person gets hospitalized,
he is given treatment in a day care centre in a hospital.
After which medical advice is also given
by a qualified medical practitioner.  Then the
company will indemnify.  That means, the amount
spent will be given for the medical
expenses incurred in this treatment.
Provided further that.  Apart from this,
whatever terms and conditions there are of this coverage, be it
annual aggregate deductible,
sum, exclusions, conditions and
definitions, all the
rules and conditions within this policy will be applicable at the
time of making the claim.  Meaning, through the preamble and
operating clause, the company wants to tell
who is issuing this policy and
when it can be used.
Now friends, here comes the first
important section of this policy which matters a lot to us as a policy holder,
that is definitions
and it has two parts, standard
definitions and specific definitions.  You
can also consider it a dictionary of policy wordings.
If you are
unable to understand any word or terminology
used by the company in your policy wording document, you
can study it from here.  So let's move on to section
A.  So here comes section A.  First of all,
standard definition.  Standard definition
is that definition, that definition, that meaning
which has been defined by IRDA.  That means this
is a common definition for all the companies because this is called
standard definition.  Now it
starts here with accident i.e.
what does accident mean?
What would be considered technically?  So the meaning of accident is
written here.  Now, as it is written here in the third definition,
what is Ayush Hospital
?  What is the definition?  What
features should it have?  Should there be trades
?  All this is clearly written here that only that will be
considered a qualified Ayush hospital.
Many times we get treatment done
at an Ayush facility and later we come to know that
it was not an Ayush hospital at all.  So what
qualities and features should it have are
explained here.  Why is this section so important
?  I am saying this because inside this section
you will get the definition of every word and what
it means.  And this
definition is the definition which is legally defined.  This
means that if any claim is
legally challenged under this policy contract,
these definitions will be referred to.
Because in common language we
understand very different meanings of small things.
Now as you can see here,
day care treatment.  Now,
what definition do we use for day care treatment,
both in videos and in common language,
we say that it is any
treatment for which one does not have to be admitted for 24 hours.
Here is the proper definition of day care treatment.
Those medical
treatments and surgical procedures which are
undertaken under general and local anesthesia
in a hospital day care centre.  This means that
anesthesia should be administered
within a local hospital or day care center.  Which would have
otherwise required
hospitalization of more than 24 hours.  That means
this surgery or day care procedure was such that if
it had not been done then the patient would have had to be admitted for 24 hours.
So such conditions will be clearly
shown to you in this section.   The
first part of the definitions was standard
definition.  The second part is
specific definition.  Specific
definitions here mean
what definitions of these things have been given by the company issuing the policy?  So only
these will be referred.  The standard
definition is the same for all companies.
But in the specific definition, company
specific meaning of these things is written.
So, whatever you find confusing,
any word you are confused about, or
any term that the insurance company
uses during the claim process,
you can find its meaning here.
Many times this question comes up, Sir,
what is material fact?  What does it mean
?  See, every information is
written in your policy wording.  This means
the necessary information that the insurance company
collects from the policy holder along with the
connected
documents so that they can take
a better and informed decision on covering this risk.  If
you are not able to understand anything in the claim process or anything else, please
refer to the Definitions section which is the first
section in any policy wording.
Now friends comes the second section,
Section B, which is of coverage.  Three
parts are given inside it.  B point one is base
coverage, B point two is optional coverage.  That is,
those who take add ons and B point 3 is
renewal benefit.  That is,
what benefits will be available at the time of renewal?  But whatever
is written in section B is
related to your coverage only.   Do you
know what is special about Section B?
The benefits are explained to you very lightly in the brochure.
But at the time of claim,
every term and condition that the company
imposes or implements, you will find it
inside this section.  Like in this point of section B,
under hospitalization expenses, it is written that
when will the company give you the claim money?  What coverage will
be included in it?  First is the room rent,
boarding charges, nursing expenses as
provided by the hospital/nursing home.
Room rent limit shall be at actuals.
What is the room rent?  Actuals will be available as per the policy unless otherwise
specified in the policy
schedule.  That means it will be the
room rent limit mentioned in your policy document.
If it is not written then the
actual expenses of room rent will be given.
What will be covered for ICU
?  Apart from this, there are surgeon's fees,
anesthetist's fees, medical
practitioner, consultant, specialist fees
during hospitalization forming part
of the hospital bill.  The fees of all these doctors will
also be payable.
Investigative
treatments and diagnostic procedures
directly related to hospitalization, i.e.,
tests and diagnostic
procedures directly related to treatment, will be
covered if mentioned in the hospital bill.  Medicines and
Drugs Prescribed in Writing by
Medical Practitioners: The medicines and
drugs prescribed by the doctor will also be
available in this.  Apart from this, blood
transfusion, surgical appliances, available
consumables, non-medical items
are allowed under the policy.  Operation theatre charges,
cost of prosthetics and other devices/
equipment if implanted internally
during surgery.  Any
device that has to be implanted during the surgery will also be covered.
Now these things have been written very clearly
by the company.  It's
not just us who read them carefully.  If there is any bill
which the company does not approve.  And if you
know
what expenses are covered under hospitalization expenses, then the
company can never escape
from its coverage.
She cannot refuse to claim any genuine expenses.  Look, it is
clearly stated
what expenses the company will cover here.
So, in section B,
you can see the rest of the expenses and other details in the same manner from here.
What will be covered under home health care
?  What will be the conditions is also written.
What are the conditions of domicile?
What is AYUSH treatment?  How will pre and post be
covered?
What will be the conditions for donor expenses?  Each and every thing is
written in absolute detail.  Now don't
read it completely.  But at least when
you go for treatment, or if you are planning any planned surgery
, you
can directly go to that section before that.  You
can go to the point where you are
looking for that thing directly.  So the
first point of section B we looked at was base
coverage.  Base coverage here means the
coverage that
comes under the standard policy.  You do not have to do any add-on or any separate modification.
If you
buy a policy, this coverage will be included in your plan by default.
Section B which
is of benefits.  Its second part
is optional covers.  You already know the optional covers
which you have the option to take.  This means that
you will have to take the add-on separately.  If you
feel the need, pay extra money and you can
get that add-on.  The special thing about optional covers is that they contain
features that you may need
but are not part of the standard policy.
But these are such features that
not every policy holder needs them.
So whoever needs it can choose them,
pay extra premium and
add them to the policy.  You can also see all these add-ons
from here.  Like
what is Protect Benefit?  What is Plus Benefit
?  And each term and
condition is written here.  It has been explained in full detail.
And the truth is that health
insurance companies
refer to these conditions while approving or rejecting a claim.
Think about how your preparation will
be?  How prepared will you be when you also
know these terms and conditions.  You ca
n't read everything in the beginning.  So at least you must check the
terms and conditions of the particular section at the time of claim.
So that you can
know whether the rejection
or the amount deducted by the company
aligns with what is written in their policy wordings or not.  This means that you can
directly catch the wrong practices of the company.
So section two is of optional benefits.
Whatever add-ons you have, you will
see them inside this wording.  You can see the definition and other details of whatever add-on you choose
from here.  Within Section B,
i.e. within the benefits section, the
third point given here is Renewal
Benefit.  Renewal benefit means
what benefit will you get if you renew the policy
?  Now it is not necessary that you get three different parts in the benefit
section in all the plans of all the companies.
But you will
definitely find the benefits section.  Some companies will
show you add-ons under a benefit section
and will also show renewal benefits in the same section.
But in this policy, the
third point of renewal benefit is written separately.
If you renew your preventive health checkup,
you get extra benefits here.
But inside every policy wording,
you will definitely find a section on benefits.
That too after the preamble and operating clause.
Now friends, our third important section
comes, Section C, in which you will find the
waiting period.  That is, after how much time
which treatment will be covered.  Standard
exclusions are those exclusions defined by IRDA.
Specific Exclusions
Policy specific exclusions are treatments
that the policy will never cover.  So the
C section will tell you whether your claim is going to be
approved or rejected.  So now
we have come to Section C in the Policy Wording document.  The
first point here is the
waiting period.  See, waiting period
means that after how much time you have purchased the policy,
which treatment will be covered,
that defines the waiting period.  So the
first point comes about the
waiting period of pre-existing disease. Pre-existing disease
means that
if you have any medical condition before you have purchased the policy
and you declare it, then after how much time will it be
covered.  For example, here the
waiting period for pre-existing disease is
written as 36 months.  That condition will be covered after 3 years.
It is also written that if
you increase the sum insured, a separate waiting period will be applicable.
What are the other conditions, they are
also written here.  Secondly, there is a waiting
period for a specific disease or a
specific procedure.  These are listed
surgeries and listed treatments whose
waiting period can be from 24 months to 12 months
under your plan.  That means the
listed treatments, these surgeries, will also be
covered after 12 to 24 months of purchasing the policy.
You can see how much is written inside your policy wording.
This specific waiting period.  The most important thing is that
you will see these conditions here as to
how the waiting period will be implemented.
Apart from this, you will
also get an exact list of diseases and after how much time they will be
covered.  Like
this illness is shown here first.  This
particular illness has exactly the
name of that disease and its diagnosis written on it.
These will be covered after 24 months.
After this there are some surgical procedures.  Some are
minor surgeries.  If any of these
surgeries are done, they will also be
covered after 24 months.  How easy it is to see this thing.  The
doctor has recommended a particular surgery.
You will directly
go to this section under section C and
see in the list of specific diseases whether
this surgery is prescribed or not.  You will know
whether it has a 24-month waiting period
or not.  Because it is very confusing.
You can't remember all these things.  So
directly in section C of Policy Wordings
you have to check this list under Specific Diseases.
This policy will not cover any treatment other than accidental treatment within the first 30 days of purchasing the policy.
Be it due to sickness, illness or
any surgery, only
accident treatment will be covered.  And the special
thing is that the
waiting period of 30 days is common in all the plans.  Let
me tell you another fact about the waiting period that if
you already have a policy in place and
you have migrated or ported within this plan or to a new plan, then
this
waiting period waives on the basis of
how long your coverage has been
continuing.  So this 30 day
waiting period gets waived if you have migrated your old policy.
Similarly, specific and prior
waiting periods are also waived in
continuation policies.  But if you are taking a fresh policy for the first time, then
you will definitely have to check such waiting period in your policy.
Now after the waiting period, the second point comes
standard exclusion.
Under standard exclusions, IRDA has defined
that you can keep these exclusions in your policy.  That
means it will be fine if you don't cover it.  The
first is
Investigation and Evaluation.  That means
you just get the test done.  If no treatment is being done
then it will not be covered.  I have
made a separate video on this.  I have already made videos on the exclusions of Optima Secure
and many other plans.
You can go and see that too.  Obesity
is generally excluded but if these conditions are
fulfilled then obesity
surgery and bariatric surgery can also be covered under it.
So you will get very important terms
and conditions here.  If a
health insurance claim is rejected.
Some money is also deducted.
You will get its point within section C only.  Be
it a waiting period, standard
exclusion or any specific
exclusion.  You will
find all three of these inside section C.  So you do
n't have to go anywhere else directly.  Have to
come to section C.  If there is a waiting period,
check the waiting period.  Otherwise, standard
exclusions or
specific exclusions come after this.  Specific
exclusions means this is HDFC Ago's
Optima Secure plan.  What are the exclusions of this plan,
they are mentioned inside it.
Therefore,
everyone may have an idea about standard exclusion.  It should be the same in all companies.
But within the specific exclusions, there are
some points which may be
different from the rest of the plan.  So definitely
read that.  It
is also very important to read the specific exclusions because these are plan
specific exclusions.  And the 95%
portion in this will be common to you in every plan.
But within the 5% exclusion,
some surgeries and some therapies may be included.
Those who are excluded from this plan.
So that 5% is very important for you to read.
Therefore, this specific exclusion is
much more than the standard exclusion.
Now friends comes a very
important and technical section that is section
D.  Inside this you will find the terms and conditions.
All the clauses that we mention
or want to cancel the policy like portability, migration, free
look period.
What are the conditions behind these,
what clauses are included?  You will
get that information inside section D.  That means, any
technical aspect related to the coverage of your policy
, continuity,
cancellation, moratorium period,
you can check it inside this D section.
Now imagine your question is only about this
section.  You can ignore the entire policy wording
document.  You have to
go directly inside this section.
Friends, we have come to Section D - General
Terms and Clauses.  The first
part in this is what are Standard Terms and
Conditions Clauses?  They are
written inside it.  In which the first point is
disclosure of information.  That means
you have to tell everything honestly.  Any event
of misrepresentation, giving wrong information
or giving wrong description, non-
disclosure.  If you conceal any material fact, the
policy may become void.  It is
not the case that only
those conditions which are beneficial for the company are written in this section.   There
is a lot for policy holders too.
Regarding claim settlement, it is written here
that the company will have to settle
or reject any claim.  Age the case may be
within 15 days from the date of receipt
of intimation.  Accept or reject the claim within 15 days.
Whatever
decision the company has to take, it will have to take it within 15 days.  In
these cases the company delays in paying the claim money.  If the
claim has been approved but the
money is not received, then the
policy holder will have to pay interest at the rate of 2% more than the bank's interest rate.  The
number of days for which this delay has occurred.
This is how multiple policies are closed
here.  You have more than one health
insurance policy.  So,
you will find all the conditions written here on how you can use it.  The moratorium
period should cover 60 continuous months.  There is a
moratorium period of 5 years.
Which claims can be rejected after that
?  Which ones are not, you will find them inside this.
What is the definition of fraud?  Which
claim can be termed as fraud?  Which claim
or act can be termed as fraud?
All that is explained here.  And what will happen
after that?  Free look period means you
buy the policy.  After how many days
can you cancel the policy without any
deduction?  What are the terms and conditions, that is
written.  The conditions for policy renewal are written.
When can the company not refuse to renew the policy
?  What are your coverages and
rights that the company must
maintain as it is in continuity?
What are the guidelines for portability?  What are the terms
and conditions?  Migration:
If you want to change your plan within the same company,
what are its rules?  If you want to cancel the policy,
what is the process?  And
how much premium will you get back and how much money will you
get back?  All that is written here.
Want to pay premium in installments.
What are its terms and conditions?  Grace
period is mentioned separately.  So in this
way you will find all the terms and conditions
written here.  These questions come up very often.
Sir, is this 10 times, five
times cumulative bonus, booster plus
bonus?  Such bonuses may be removed in the future.
Absolutely.  It is
written in their conditions that there is a possibility of
revision of terms of the policy including the
premium rates.  Premiums may also increase
and coverage may also be increased or decreased.
But every company will have to take approval from IRDA.  Only
after that he can do it.
Withdrawal of Policy Can policies be
withdrawn?  It can definitely be done.
Many companies have withdrawn.
SBI's Arogya Plus plan has been withdrawn.
HDFC Ago's My Health Suraksha Plan has been
withdrawn.  Some plans of every company keep getting
withdrawn.  And for that too, they can do this
only after taking permission from IRD.
But you will find all the conditions
here.  Who can you make your nominee
?  What needs to be done for grievances
?  If there is any complaint against the company, the claim gets
rejected.  So what is its step by
step process?  Level One: Where do you need to
write?  Where do I need to call?
Where should level two be written?  There is a
helpline number and email
ID for senior citizens.  There is a separate contact number for women.
So see how detailed information
is there here that no matter what situation you are in,
when you are in trouble,
every information regarding health insurance claim
is given here.  After that friends, the next
part comes specific within these general terms and conditions.
That earlier condition
was standard which is almost same for all the companies.
Now these are the specific conditions
regarding this plan, in which the
utilization of sum insured i.e.
in which sequence will your sum insured be
used?  Brother, when the first claim comes, the
annual aggregate deductible will be
deducted first.  Then the base sum insured,
then cumulative bonus and plus benefit will be
used.  Then Secure Benefit then
Automatic Restore Benefit.  It is
also stated that if there is a single claim, it
cannot exceed your Basic Sum Assured, Cumulative Bonus Plus Benefit and Secure Benefit combined.  These
conditions clarify them completely.
If you have any doubt
in your mind.  In addition,
loadings can be applied.  The opposite of discount
is loading.  The
premium is lower in discount.  The premium increases with loading.  If
a policy holder
is seriously ill or has a specific condition, the
companies can also increase the premium.  There
is also a loading limit.
Loading cannot be taken for anything more than 100%.
And total loading cannot exceed 150% for each insured person.
Endorsements i.e. how changes can be made within the policy.
What will the premium tier be?  That is, information about how many zones the zone has been divided into has
also been given separately.
And is there zone based copayment or not?
Very important information.  It is written here that
no copayment shall apply if the insured person
changes the zone to get treatment in Tier 1, i.e., if he/she changes the zone and gets treatment, then
no copayment will be charged, but the
policy must be purchased in the correct zone.
You will get all this deep and important information
in this section.  Terms and
Conditions Inside the Terms and Clauses section.
If there is a dispute,
you can file any case in Indian courts and subject to Indian law.  So this
completes our Section D, in which
every important condition related to the policy that
we have known will be written here.  So if you want to see
any term and condition of your health insurance plan, you
can go and check it inside your section.  If you want
me to make a separate dedicated video on any section or point or topic in this entire policy wording.  Let me
explain to him what it is and
how it works.  Whatever you have
seen here, you have seen different terms
, you can tell me about it in the comment section.
I will make a separate dedicated
video on them as well.
Our last section in the policy wording structure is
Section E – Other Terms and
Clauses.  After that I will also
tell you the annexure.  I will also explain to you what these annexures are and
what information is written in them.
Section E
is named exactly like Section D.  Other Terms and Clauses.  But this
is a very important section and is totally different from that.
If you have any question related to claim
, what is the claim procedure?
What will be the cashless claim?  What
documents are required?  You will
get all that information inside this section.  If you have a
question in your mind that I want to take a claim,
how do I file?  What should I do?  So you have to
come directly to section A.
You can ignore the rest of the policy.  If you
want to know about the claim process.
So the first point is the claim
procedure.
When do you need to give intimation about the claim?  When to tell the company by
calling.  In case of any emergency
hospitalization, it is
mandatory for the company to file an intimate claim within 24 hours of admission.  And if there
is a planned hospitalization, you know that
I will be admitted on that day and will get treatment,
you should inform the company 48 hours or two days before that
and you can get the claim approval.
Procedure of Cashless Claims in India.
If you want to claim from a cashless hospital in India
, without paying any money in advance for treatment
, what are its terms and
conditions?  What is its process?  It is
explained in detail here.  Process of
Cashless Claim Outside India.
If you want to take a cashless claim outside India, then
its terms and conditions are
mentioned here.  You must check in your plan.
These are very important things.  Apart from this,
procedure for cashless claim in home
health care.
What will be the claim process for getting treatment at home?  What
documents are required?  When do you need to get approval
?  After this some conditions have been mentioned.
You can find out what conditions need to be fulfilled within India to get approval for cashless facility.  Reimbursement
claim means that cashless treatment was not provided in the hospital
or there is no cashless tie-up in the hospital.
You have already paid for the treatment and
later want to get the money back from the company, then what
kind of claims can be there are explained here.
And what is their time limit?  Many
times they also say that it has been a month since I took the treatment.
I did not even file a claim for
reimbursement.  So here the time limit is mentioned as
30 days and 15 days.  According to this,
you have to
file reimbursement claim within this time limit as per the
policy conditions.  The documents required for reimbursement claim are
mentioned separately here.  You
can also read these carefully during any claim.
And it's not like you have to remember all of this.
Exactly when the claim has come,
you will get the information directly in the claim process under these terms and conditions in the E section.
Now the question arises that where will you make the claim
intimation?  So
look here with in India, if
these claims come within India then this is the information.  This
is a toll free number.  You can take a screenshot of these.
You can save the number.   If you
are outside India then you have to dial this number.
You can email here.
You should have this information.  Your
family members should also have this.  If
any emergency arises.  Therefore this information
is very important.  Apart from this, if you
want to submit the claim documents
at any address, then
you have to send the claim documents within India to this address.
Hard copies are
original copies.  And if this
is an outside India claim, a travel policy claim,
then you can send it to this address.
Now friends, you have understood these five sections from A to E.
What details will you find inside these?
Now friends, it is the turn of Annexure A.
Let us see what the company has said inside Annexure A.
Friends, inside Ener A, the
company has given the contact details of the
officers of the Insurance Ombudsman.
Insurance of Birdsman i.e.
Insurance Ombudsman in Hindi is that institution.  If you have any
complaint related to your claim,
against the insurance company, against the agent, that is, if
you have any complaint related to the insurance policy,
then you can approach the Insurance Ombudsman.
But the condition is that first you will have to
file a complaint with the insurance company itself.   You do
not get the right answer from there, the answer does
not come at all or you are not satisfied with the answer.
Then you can complain to the Insurance Ombudsman.
And these have dedicated addresses.  Which address will come
according to your state, your union territory
?  What are their contact details
?  What is email ID?  All that
is explained here.  Now
why is this detail given inside Ener A?  Because as I
told you, companies do not decide this sequence or structure on their
own.  IRDA
guidelines state that in the form you must mention the
office
addresses, email IDs, contact details and
state names of all the insurance observers.  That
means, at the time of claim rejection,
before directly filing a legal case, you
can write to the office of the Insurance Ombudsman.
I will give you the video of making online complaint
in the description of this video.
I made it separately.  You
can lodge a complaint while sitting at home.  However, sometimes it takes a lot of time
because there is a lot of
workload in the Insurance and Businessman offices. It takes
6 months, 8 months or even a year to
hear the complaints.  But still
you can put forward your point here.  The second
annexure comes friends, Annexure B.  The
items for which coverage is not available in
the policy.  That means you will
not get their coverage under the policy.  These are non-medical items
which we also call consumables.
Friends, this is List One of Annexure B, in which
you get a total of 68 non-medical
items.  Whose coverage you will not get under a
standard health insurance policy.  That
means these are those items,
if their names appear anywhere in the hospital billing
then the company is
not going to give you the money for them.  Now, the
items listed in Annex B are 68 non-
medical items, although these are excluded,
but if the companies mention their coverage in their policy contract,
then
you can get coverage for them also.
Only the items in List One are shown here in Optima Secure, the HDF share within NXer B.
But there are total four lists.
These four lists contain different non-
medical items.  Some plans have
empty list one cover.  As
shown here, 68 items will be covered,
and some plans
cover all four lists.  Optima Secure
plan has the Protect benefit which
gives you coverage for these 68 non-medical items.
But you
can also look at the remaining three lists in your policy wording and
check which list
you get coverage for.
I have
made a separate dedicated video on non-medical consumable items
in which I have explained all the four lists
and along with this I have also
told that if you do not want their deduction from your claim
and they are
not covered under your policy then
what will you have to do in billing,
what will you have to tell the hospital so that your money is not deducted,
you will find that video in the description,
I will give it to you there in the name of non-medical consumable items.  By clicking on the link found in
front of non-medical items i.e. consumables,
you
can see all the four lists of IRDA and
I have also explained separately very well what items are there in it.
Now friends comes Ener C.  Annexure
A, B and C We saw three annexures.   The
plan chart comes inside Ener C.
Now there are many variants of Optima Secure.
What are the features in all those variants
?  What are the differences?  You
can notice that here.  Here is their
schedule of benefits.  Which
variants are Optima Security available in?
This is what we are talking about Optima Secure.
Optima Super Secure, Optima Secure
Global and Optima Secure Global Plus which
also give you global coverage.
Apart from this, Optima Select is a free policy
available in the market.  The
cheaper variant of Optimite Optima Secure is also
available here.  The
differences in coverage within all these are shown to you in the
form of a difference sheet in the form of a table of benefits.
So if you want to
understand the difference between these six-seven plans,
what is the sum insured, what is covered, what will
not be covered, then you
can easily see it from here, how much money will you get for what, how
many options of deductible are there,
you will get all this in detail.  Now in these
annexures the company
can show things in different ways.  For example, here is
an empty list of non-medical items.  The
remaining three lists are not
shown.  In the policy wordings of some plans,
you may
not find a plan chart section
explaining the different plans.  Coverage and
benefits were differentiated.  It is possible that
this may not be available.  How much and how health insurance
companies disclose this information is
their own
decision.  But the IRDA defined
structure of policy wordings is going to
remain the same, within which you will get preamble and
operating clause.  Along with this, the
most important part is from Section A
to Section A, in which you will find definitions,
benefits, waiting period and
exclusions, standard general terms and
clauses and apart from this, a
separate section for other terms and conditions will also be available.
Apart from this,
I have also told you what information is there inside Ener.  So
friends, you have learned
what is the structure of health insurance policy wordings.  While
taking the policy wordings of any plan, it is necessary to mention these sections in it
and
you
can directly jump to the section to which your query is related.  I hope
this one video will solve most of your
doubts and queries.
Because not only have you
understood the structure of the policy wordings and
what sections you will find, but
you have also found out where the question that was
going on in my mind for the last 6 months is
written in my own policy wording.
So what we say is that the
companies have not told anything or something
is hidden.  Nothing is hidden.  The only
thing that always bothers us is
our ignorance.  Because it
is very difficult to understand so much technical language.
But if a claim gets complicated, all that
hard work is
nothing compared to the struggle to recover from the loss.  And now you
know very well
what will be written where in the policy wordings and to
verify this you
can also check your own policy wordings to see whether the
benefits and other
sections are mentioned in it or not and whether
you got the information you need there or
not.  If you liked the video and the
information, then to show your love and
support, you can like the video
and definitely subscribe to the channel
so that you keep getting similar informational
videos which are actually going to be useful to you.
I Ravindra
Singh will meet you in the next video.
Till then take care, stay fit and stay
healthy.  Jai Hind.